<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="sound_description">
        <item>eɪ::The \'long a\' /eɪ/ is a 2-sound vowel. It is the middle sound in the word \'cake\' /keɪk/.\n\nTo pronounce the sound, begin with the tongue pushed somewhat forward but in a neutral position in the mouth. Then, as the jaw closes slightly, move the body of the tongue upward until it is near the tooth ridge—similar to the position of a \'y sound\' /y/. The front sides of the tongue touch the inside of the top teeth at the end of the sound.</item>
        <item>æ::The front of the tongue is pushed further forward and is held lower in the mouth when forming the \'short a\' /æ/ sound than with any other vowel sound. The tip of the tongue will touch the inside of the bottom front teeth. The body of the tongue is rounded slightly upward. The jaw is lowered and the lips are held apart, allowing the entire oral cavity to remain open.</item>
        <item>i::The tongue is forward, with the body of the tongue near the tooth ridge. (The tongue is higher in the mouth for this sound than for any other vowel in English.) Because the tongue is so high, the jaw is relatively closed during the \'long e\' /i/ sound. The sides of the tongue touch the top, side teeth during the sound.</item>
        <item>ɛ::The \'short e\' /ɛ/ sound is a relatively relaxed vowel sound. The middle of the tongue rounds slightly upward and the sides of the tongue may lightly touch the top and bottom side teeth. The lips and jaw are loose and relaxed.</item>
        <item>ɑɪ::The \'long i\' /ɑɪ/ is a 2-sound vowel that ends in a brief \'y sound\' /y/.\n\nPart 1: At the beginning of the sound, the tongue is low and touches the bottom, side teeth.\n\nPart 2: As the jaw closes slightly, the body of the tongue moves upward until it is near the tooth ridge, similar to the position of a \'y sound\' /y/. The front sides of the tongue touch the inside of the top, side teeth</item>
        <item>ɪ::The lips are relaxed and the central/front area of the tongue is in the central/high area of the mouth for this sound. The overall neutrality and relaxed tongue and lip position is why it is one of the pronunciations used in an unstressed vowel position.</item>
        <item>oʊ::The \'long o\' /oʊ/ is a two-sound vowel that ends in a brief \'w sound\' /w/.\n\nPart 1: The body of the tongue is pushed back and in a low-to-mid mouth position and the bottom teeth can be felt along the sides of the tongue.\n\nPart 2: The sound moves into a \'w sound\' /w/ by raising the jaw slightly while closing the lips into a small circle. The body of the tongue moves upward until the tongue is near the back of the hard palate.</item>
        <item>ɑ::The vocal tract is very open for the production of the \'short o\' /ɑ/ sound. In fact, the jaw is held more open and the back of the tongue is held lower for this sound than any other American English vowel sound pronunciation. The tongue touches the inside of the bottom teeth so that the top of the tongue is nearly even with the top of the bottom teeth. The lips are held open and kept rounded, but relaxed</item>
        <item>ju::The \'long u\' /yu/ is a 2-sound vowel similar to a \'y sound\' /y/ followed by an \'oo sound\' /u/.\n\nPart 1: The \'long u\' /yu/ begins with the jaw mostly closed and tip of the tongue very close to the tooth ridge (similar to a \'y sound\' /y/).\n\nPart 2: The sound transitions into an \'oo sound\' /u/ by closing the lips into a small circle while lowering the front of the tongue. At the same time as the front of the tongue lowers, the back of the tongue raises.</item>
        <item>ʌ::The body of the tongue is relaxed and set low in the mouth. The sides of the tongue lightly touch the bottom teeth during the formation of the sound. The jaw is kept in a neutral position, and the lips are relaxed.\n\nThe overall relaxed nature of the formation of this sound is why it is commonly used for the pronunciation of the vowel sound of an unstressed syllable. The \'short i\' /ɪ/ sound may also be used in an unstressed syllable, but short u /ʌ/ or schwa /ə/ are more common.</item>
        <item>ʊ::To create the \'other u\' /ʊ/ sound, the back of the tongue is raised to a mid-high position. The sides of the tongue may touch the top teeth toward the back of the mouth. The jaw is slightly closed and the lips are pulled into a loose circle.</item>
        <item>u::To create the \'oo sound\' /u/, the lips are pulled into a tense, small circle. In addition, the back of the tongue is raised to a high position and sides of the tongue may touch the top teeth at the back of the mouth.</item>
        <item>ɔ::The entire tongue is pushed back and kept low during the pronunciation of the \'aw sound\' /ɔ/. The bottom side teeth can be felt alongside the front of the tongue during the sound. The back of the tongue has only a slight rounding upward at the very rear of the mouth. The lips are made into an oval shape, and may stick slightly outward.\n\nThe North American \'aw sound\' /ɔ/ is one of the sounds with the greatest variation in pronunciation even within the continent. Some regions of the United States do not consider this to be a different sound from the \'short o\' /ɑ/. However, in many regions of the country it is a unique sound; therefore it is described separately.</item>
        <item>ɔɪ::The \'oi sound\' /ɔɪ/ is a two-sound vowel that ends in a brief \'y sound\' /y/.\n\nPart 1: At the beginning of the sound the jaw is open about mid-way and the body of the tongue is in a low position in the mouth. The bottom teeth can be felt along the sides of the tongue.\n\nPart 2: Then the jaw closes slightly. The body of the tongue moves upward until it is near the tooth ridge, similar to the position of a \'y sound\' /y/. The front sides of the tongue touch the inside of the top, side teeth.</item>
        <item>aʊ::The \'ow sound\' /aʊ/ is a two-sound vowel that ends in a brief \'w sound\' /w/.\n\nPart 1: The sound begins with the jaw open and the body of the tongue in a low position in the mouth. The bottom teeth can be felt along the sides of the tongue.\n\nPart 2: Then, as the jaw closes, the lips close into a small circle similar to the position of a \'w sound\' /w/. The body of the tongue moves upward until the tongue is near the back of the hard palate.</item>
        <item>ɚ::Schwa+r\' /ɚ/ is an r-controlled vowel. This strange sound is created the same way as the \'r sound\' /r/, and therefore has the same two options available for pronouncing it.\n\nThe first option is to raise the back of the tongue so that the sides of the tongue touch the back teeth. The center of the back of the tongue is lower and the air travels through this groove to create the sound.\n\nAlternatively, the tip of the tongue can be raised and curled back behind the tooth ridge while the back of the tongue stays low. The air still travels over the back of the tongue, but moves more along the sides and tip.\n\nThe tip of the tongue never touches the tooth ridge during the American English \'schwa+r\' /ɚ/ or \'r sound\' /r/.</item>
        <item>ɑr::The \'ar sound\' /ɑr/ is an r-controlled vowel. Technically this sound is two distinct sounds (vowel sound+\'r sound\' /r/). It is presented with the name \'ar sound\' /ɑr/ to distinguish the fact that the vowel portion of the sound is different from the various pronunciations commonly used for the letter \'a\' spelling.\n\nThe \'ar sound\' /ɑr/ begins with the tongue in the position of a \'short o\' /ɑ/ sound. The tip and center of the tongue are set low, inside the bottom teeth. The top of the tongue is nearly even with the top of the bottom teeth.\n\nTo transition to the \'r\' portion of the sound, the body of the tongue moves upward. The mid-section of the tongue rises so the sides of the tongue touch the middle teeth. The air travels over the body of the tongue to create the /r/ portion of the sound. (NOTE: The secondary method of producing the /r/ may be used to produce second portion of the \'ar sound\' /ɑr/ instead of this technique.)</item>
        <item>ɔr::The \'or sound\' /ɔr/ is an r-controlled vowel. Technically this sound is two distinct sounds (vowel sound+r sound). It is presented here under the name \'or sound\' /ɔr/ to distinguish the fact that the vowel portion of the sound is different from the various pronunciations commonly used for the \'o\' spelling.\n\nThe \'or sound\' /ɔr/ begins with lips rounded. The tongue is pushed back and held middle-low in the mouth, similar to the beginning of a \'long o\' /oʊ/ sound. Although the International Phonetic Alphabet transcription shows that the or sound begins with the symbol used for the \'aw sound\' /ɔ/, note that the tongue is not as far back as it is during that sound.\n\nTo transition to the /r/ portion of the sound, the lips relax and the body of the tongue moves upward and forward. The mid-section of the tongue raises so the sides of the tongue touch the middle teeth. The air travels over the body of the tongue to create the /r/ portion of the sound. (NOTE: The secondary method of producing the /r/ may be used to produce second portion of the /ɔr/ instead of this technique.)</item>
        <item>ɛr::The \'air sound\' /ɛr/ is an r-controlled vowel. Technically this sound is two distinct sounds (vowel sound+\'r sound\' /r/). It is presented here under the name \'air sound\' to distinguish the fact that the vowel portion of the sound is different from the \'long a\' /eɪ/ (although the sound\'s spellings are very similar to those for the \'long a\' /eɪ/).\n\nThe \'air sound\' /ɛr/ begins with the tongue rounded slightly upward in the middle of the mouth. The sides of the tongue may lightly touch the bottom teeth during the formation of the beginning of this sound.\n\nTo transition to the /r/ portion of the sound, the body of the tongue moves upward and forward. The mid-section of the tongue raises so the sides of the tongue touch the mid-side teeth. The air travels over the body of the tongue to create the /r/ portion of the sound. (NOTE: The secondary method of producing the /r/ may be used to produce second portion of the \'air sound\' /ɛr/ instead of this technique.)</item>
        <item>b::The \'b sound\' /b/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'p sound\' /p/.\n\nTo create the /b/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract by closing the lips. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The aspiration for a /b/ is less than the aspiration for a /p/.</item>
        <item>ʧ::The \'ch sound\' /ʧ/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'j sound\' /ʤ/.\n\nTo create the /ʧ/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the tip of the tongue presses against the back tooth ridge while the sides of the tongue press against the upper side teeth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released with friction (similar to the friction of an sh sound).\n\nMany English language learning pronunciation students often find it helpful to think of the /ʧ/ as stopping the air similar to a \'t sound\' (but with the tongue a bit further back on the tooth ridge), and then releasing it with the friction of an \'sh sound\' /ʃ/.</item>
        <item>d::The \'d sound\' /d/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'t sound\' /t/.\n\nTo create the /d/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the tip of the tongue presses against the tooth ridge while the sides of the tongue press against the upper side teeth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The aspiration for a /d/ is less than the aspiration for a /t/.\n\nAdvanced ESL/ELL pronunciation students should be aware that when the /d/ is followed by an \'l sound\' /l/ or an \'n sound\' /n/, the aspiration of the /d/ is not released in the same manner as before other sounds. Instead, a lateral aspiration is used in the /d+l/ combination, and a nasal aspiration is used in the /d+n/ combination.</item>
        <item>f::The \'f sound\' /f/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'v sound\' /v/.\n\nTo create the /f/, the jaw is held nearly closed. The upper backside of the bottom lip is pressed very lightly into the bottom of the top teeth. Air is pushed out the mouth between the top teeth and the upper backside of the bottom lip. This sound is to be a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being produced for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.\n\nThe lips are kept mostly relaxed during the production of the /f/. A common error English language learners make is overproducing this sound by curling the bottom lip under the top teeth. This creates problems when linking other sounds to and from the /f/.</item>
        <item>g::The \'g sound\' /g/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'k sound\' /k/.\n\nTo create the /g/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the back of the tongue lifts and presses against the soft palate at the back of the mouth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The amount of aspiration used to produce a /g/ is less than that for a /k/.</item>
        <item>h::The \'h sound\' /h/ is unvoiced, and the vocal cords do not vibrate during the production of this sound.\n\nTo create the h sound, the deep back of the tongue slightly constricts within the throat. The upper/front part of the tongue as well as the lips will often move into the shape of surrounding sounds at the same time as the h sound is being produced.\n\nA common error English language learners make is overproducing the /h/ by constricting the tongue too much within the throat or by voicing the sound.</item>
        <item>ʤ::The \'j sound\' /ʤ/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'ch sound\' /ʧ/.\n\nTo create the /ʤ/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the tip of the tongue presses against the back tooth ridge while the sides of the tongue press against the upper side teeth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released with friction (similar to the friction of a \'zh sound\' /ʒ/).\n\nEnglish language learners often find it helpful to think of the /ʤ/ as stopping the air similar to a \'d sound\' /d/ (but with the tongue a bit further back on the tooth ridge), and then releasing it with the friction of a /ʒ/.</item>
        <item>k::The \'k sound\' /k/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'g sound\' /g/.\n\nTo create the /k/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the back of the tongue lifts and presses against the soft palate at the back of the mouth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The amount of aspiration used to produce a /k/ is greater than that used for a /g/.</item>
        <item>l::There are two \'l sound\' formations—also known as allophones of the \'l sound\': a \'light l\' and a \'velar\' (or dark) \'l\'. The \'velar l\' is represented by the International Phonetic Alphabet symbol /ɫ/.\n\nThe following is a description for the light l; hereafter simply referred to as the \'l sound\' /l/.\n\nTo create the /l/, the tip of the tongue is placed against the middle of the tooth ridge. The sound is created when air travels alongside the tip of the tongue, between the front of the tongue and the side teeth.</item>
        <item>m::To create the \'m sound\' /m/, the lips are pressed together, causing the air to be blocked from leaving the mouth. The soft palate drops, allowing air to pass out through the nose. The sound is voiced, so the vocal cords vibrate while producing it.</item>
        <item>n::To create the \'n sound\' /n/, the air is blocked from leaving the mouth by pressing the tip against the tooth ridge and the sides of the front of the tongue against the side teeth. The soft palate drops, allowing air to pass out through the nose. The sound is voiced, so the vocal cords vibrate while producing it</item>
        <item>ŋ::To create the \'ng sound\' /ŋ/, air is prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the back of the tongue lifts and presses against the soft palate at the back of the mouth. The soft palate drops, allowing air to pass out through the nose. The sound is voiced, so the vocal cords vibrate while producing it.</item>
        <item>p::The \'p sound\' /p/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'b sound\' /b/.\n\nTo create the /p/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract by closing the lips. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The aspiration for a /p/ is greater than the aspiration for a /b/.</item>
        <item>r::There are two different ways to create an \'r sound\' /r/, and although the tongue placement is quite different between the two, the sound they produce is very similar. An important aspect of the American /r/ is that the tip of the tongue never touches the tooth ridge during this sound!\n\nMethod 1 (solid): The back of the tongue is raised so the sides of the tongue touch the back teeth. The center of the back of the tongue is lower and the air travels through this groove to create the sound. The tip of the tongue may point upward, or may be left low.\n\nMethod 2 (dashed): The tip of the tongue is raised and curled back behind the tooth ridge while the back of the tongue stays low.\n\nStudents should experiment to find the most effective individual method. Also, the /r/ interacts with adjacent sounds, which can result in positions that are a combination of the above methods.</item>
        <item>s::The \'s sound\' /s/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'z sound\' /z/.\n\nTo create the /s/, the front of the tongue is placed close to the tooth ridge. The tip of the tongue should be close to the upper backside of the top front teeth. The tongue is kept tense as air is pushed between a small groove along the center of the tip of the tongue and the front of the tooth ridge. The front sides of the tongue touch the side teeth toward the front of the mouth. The lips are held slightly tense during the sound.\n\nThe /s/ is a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being produced for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.</item>
        <item>ʃ::The \'sh sound\' /ʃ/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'zh sound\' /ʒ/.\n\nTo create the /ʃ/, air is forced between a wide groove in the center of the front of the tongue and the back of the tooth ridge. The sides of the blade of the tongue may touch the side teeth. The lips are kept slightly tense, and may protrude somewhat during the production of the sound.\n\nThis sound is a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being produced for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.</item>
        <item>t::The \'t sound\' /t/ is unvoiced (the vocal cords do not vibrate while producing it), and is the counterpart to the voiced \'d sound\' /d/.\n\nTo create the /t/, air is briefly prevented from leaving the vocal tract when the tip of the tongue presses against the tooth ridge while the sides of the tongue press against the upper side teeth. The sound is aspirated when the air is released. The aspiration for a /t/ is greater than the aspiration for a /d/, especially when it is the first sound of a word or the first sound of a stressed syllable.\n\nAdvanced ESL/ELL pronunciation students should be aware of /t/ allophones, of which there are many. The /t/ is usually only pronounced as described above in the following circumstances:\n\nit is the first sound of a word\nit is the first sound of a stressed syllable\nit is preceded by a consonant sound (other than an \'r sound\' /r/ or r-controlled vowel)</item>
        <item>θ::The \'voiced th\' /ð/ and \'unvoiced th\' /θ/ sounds are the only pair of English sounds that share a single, common spelling. For that reason, the \'th sounds\' are presented together in this ESL/ELL pronunciation lesson.\n\nWith the exception of being voiced or unvoiced, the /ð/ and /θ/ are nearly identical; the tip of the tongue is placed behind the top front teeth. The friction occurs between the tip of the tongue and the top front teeth. Subtle friction may also occur between the top of the front of the tongue and the tooth ridge. The lips are kept relaxed during the production of both \'th sounds.\'\n\nAn alternative method of producing the \'th sounds\' is to place the tip of the tongue between the top and bottom front teeth. While this method will produce the correct sound, it often creates difficulties transitioning to and from other sounds. This is because the tongue needs to be so much further forward when between the front teeth as compared to behind the top front teeth.\n\nThe \'th sounds\' are continuous consonants, meaning that they should be capable of being held for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration. Because the sounds are fricatives, the majority of the sound comes from the friction of the air traveling through a small opening in the vocal tract.</item>
        <item>ð::The \'voiced th\' /ð/ and \'unvoiced th\' /θ/ sounds are the only pair of English sounds that share a single, common spelling. For that reason, the \'th sounds\' are presented together in this ESL/ELL pronunciation lesson.\n\nWith the exception of being voiced or unvoiced, the /ð/ and /θ/ are nearly identical; the tip of the tongue is placed behind the top front teeth. The friction occurs between the tip of the tongue and the top front teeth. Subtle friction may also occur between the top of the front of the tongue and the tooth ridge. The lips are kept relaxed during the production of both \'th sounds.\'\n\nAn alternative method of producing the \'th sounds\' is to place the tip of the tongue between the top and bottom front teeth. While this method will produce the correct sound, it often creates difficulties transitioning to and from other sounds. This is because the tongue needs to be so much further forward when between the front teeth as compared to behind the top front teeth.\n\nThe \'th sounds\' are continuous consonants, meaning that they should be capable of being held for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration. Because the sounds are fricatives, the majority of the sound comes from the friction of the air traveling through a small opening in the vocal tract.</item>
        <item>v::The \'v sound\' /v/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'f sound\' /f/.\n\nTo create the /v/, the jaw is held nearly closed. The upper backside of the bottom lip is pressed very lightly into the bottom of the top teeth. Air is pushed out the mouth between the top teeth and the upper backside of the bottom lip. This sound is a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being produced for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.\n\nThe lips are kept mostly relaxed during the /v/. A common error ESL/ELL students make is overproducing this sound by curling the bottom lip under the top teeth. This creates problems when linking to and from the /v/.</item>
        <item>w::The \'w sound\' /w/ is created with the jaw mostly closed and the lips formed in a small, tight circle. The sound is voiced, so the vocal cords must vibrate during the production of the sound.\n\nThe /w/ is very similar to the vowel \'oo sound\' /u/; the only difference is that the lips are slightly more closed when making the /w/. Also the /w/ is a consonant sound and cannot create a syllable as a vowel sound can.</item>
        <item>y::The tongue is extended forward, with the body of the tongue very near the tooth ridge and hard palate. Because the tongue is so high, the jaw is kept relatively closed during the formation of this sound. The sides of the tongue touch the top, side teeth during the sound. The lips are held mostly closed, and they are neither made tense nor into a circular shape.\n\nNOTE: This sound is similar to a \'long e\' /i/ in both sound and formation. However, the tongue is held closer to the tooth ridge during the \'y sound\' /y/ than during the \'long e\' /i/ sound.</item>
        <item>z::The \'z sound\' /z/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'s sound\' /s/.\n\nTo create the /z/, the front of the tongue is placed close to the tooth ridge. The tip of the tongue should be close to the upper backside of the top front teeth. The tongue is kept tense as air is pushed between a small groove along the center of the tip of the tongue and the front of the tooth ridge. The front sides of the tongue touch the side teeth toward the front of the mouth. The lips are held slightly tense during the sound.\n\nThis sound is a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being produced for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.</item>
        <item>ʒ::The \'zh sound\' /ʒ/ is voiced (the vocal cords vibrate during its production), and is the counterpart to the unvoiced \'sh sound\' /ʃ/.\n\nTo create the /ʒ/, air is forced between a wide groove in the center of the front of the tongue and the back of the tooth ridge. The sides of the blade of the tongue may touch the side teeth. The lips are kept slightly tense, and may protrude somewhat during the production of the sound.\n\nThe /ʒ/ is a continuous consonant, meaning that it should be capable of being held for a few seconds with even and smooth pronunciation for the entire duration.</item>
    </string-array>

</resources>